it's a simple question
why is pain a problem
because I don't want it
so which is first you don't want it thus
it's a problem but it's a problem with
us you don't want it
pain is not wanted pain is a problem why
is it pain a problem that's not wanted
so you make it a problem because you
don't want it
so if you stop
resisting pain as in stop trying to get
rid of the pain pain ceases to be a
problem
it gets too much pain
what is too much
well it depends what you mean by that
whether you mean too much of painfulness
of the pain
in which case well as long as you're
still alive it's not too much oh you
mean this is too much of a problem for
me so I don't want it
yeah then they cannot be too much your
thing and that's why they will give that
and that's why they will give that
example of highway robbers sawing your
limbs off one by one and if if the mind
has a will to vote that means he hasn't
fulfilled the teaching
because by by fulfilling the Dhamma it's
inconceivable to have a will towards
pain or those who cause it
is just inconceivable because he was not
conceivable to begin with but it was
your ignorance of it they was conceiving
it
but again back to the same simple
question which is a reflection anybody
can do
why is painful feeling
yeah so why would I prefer pleasure
there's nothing which is why why is it
better than
you realize you won't find
an objective answer to it you have an
attitude of not wanting pain and you
have an attitude of wanting pleasure and
your whole life is dictated by that but
if you look at that attitude as to why
is that attitude there you won't find an
answer it's good shooters attitude and
that that's the only thing the only one
and only reason for human suffering of
any kind
that's what we meant by craving mean
suffering absence of craving means
absence of suffering craving is that
attitude I
want this I don't want this
but if even if even if a person just
starts reflecting don't jump into
answering right away so just wise paint
anyway physical emotional anything any
physical emotional anything any
disagreeable feeling that I'm
experiencing why is it not wanted by
default why is that my default attitude
and by putting yourself in such a
question without providing a rational
answer you becoming aware of that problem the
you becoming aware of that problem the
problem of your attitude and sometimes
yes sometimes maybe we have to keep that
question for days as
a way of as a way of contemplation not
you have to keep repeating it just don't
answer it keep asking yourself but look
for an answer but don't answer it so
you're looking but you're not allowing
yourself to formulate it in the rational
psychologizing manner because you really
want to become aware on that emotional
level of your resistance to the
unpleasant emotion yeah you can give
this answer to that answer but
emotionally you still be resisting it or
you would still want to prolong it if
it's pleasure
but there is absolutely no
justifiable reason for not wanting pain
because if your attitude toward your
feelings matters
matters
you would feel only what you want to
feel in other words feelings would be
obeying the attitude
but the fact that you're experiencing
pain which is not wanted means you have
absolutely no say in the domain of a
feeling the domain of feeling
the domain of feeling
is unaware of your existence
feeling feelings feel pleasant feeling
feels pleasure unpleasant feeling feels
on pleasure displeasure neutral feeling
feels neither that's it
you don't exist for it
your attitude is a self-assumed parasite
upon it because of which you suffer like
the pain the experience of pain does not
it does not experience the dukkha
the experience of pain you're resisting
if you experience the dukkha that's
where you get to be free from suffering
and your sense of self and the
gratuitous assumption and everything
else but then pleasure displeasure and
neutral remains
because they were never a problem
well exactly in as much as any feeling
is inevitable for as long as you're
alive either pleasure displeasure or
neither pleasure and displeasure with
the attitude is gertrudis
option well it's all optional it's
either you have attitude where you have
undone the attitude it's not option may
be the type of Eddy but if you don't
know even the type of attitude is not
optional because in pleasure you will
always be wanting more pleasure in pain
you will always want to try and get rid
of it in a neutral feeling you is going
to distract yourself from it so your
attitudes are determined by the craving
craving has set outcomes
what's optional is how you're going to
go about it but that's already far down
the line it's not fundamental
fundamental is the attitude of wanting
no one fundamental is the attitude
fundamental is craving craving for what
were claiming for pleasure in more
pleasure cream for more pleasure in
pleasure craving for absence of pain in
pain craving for distraction oblivion in
neither pleasure nor unpleasant feeling
but that ass you can become apparently
if you start questioning yourself in
regard to the presently enduring feeling
what am I feeling now but there's
something happened to you somebody said
something you're upset pain why do I
need to well first you have to stop
projecting the blame so to speak and responsibility
the blame so to speak and responsibility
onto the world for your pain
because as long as you still think that
I'm suffering because such and such
person said this and this you have a lot
a lot of work to do basically as in you
have many views to undo
when you take responsibility for how
you're feeling and stop blaming the
world then you might be able to start
discerning your attitude in the Garter
on feeling as a primary and only one and
only source of your suffering but always
the person who is fully projected onto
the world being the reason for my pain
they can never see that because they
haven't taken response for it
but say you have taken responsibility
for you being affected by your feelings
so you stop trying to you know talk
things out with somebody upset you
nothing like you know
if they keep that sort of done to let
maintain social norms that's fine but
you don't do it as a means of escape
from your feeling you recognize that
responsibility for you being affected
what's being by what's being being felt
isn't new
not on the circumstances not on the
elements not on other people not of who
said what not of or didn't respect me
enough or they didn't do this so that
that no all of that is you you took for
granted the attitude of trying to get
rid of this on pleasure on pleasurable
feeling and then where you look where
would you go about it you are he said
this it's his fault
this happened I didn't have enough luck
it's everyone else's fault
even if people are genuinely rude and
mean to you if you suffer on account of
it that's on you
that's where the Buddha said the the the
wise monk one develop wisdom in drive
you would endure harsh words slander and
all this in the same sense you would
endure elements in the same sense you
would endure heat cold hunger
insect bites slanderous in an abusive
words cuz it's on the same level it's
just elements
but you being upset an account of it
that's a new
so why is pain a problem
in order to
reveal the attitude your attitude that
makes it a problem that feeds the
attitude that makes the problem that
feeds the attitude vicious circle in
order to reveal it you have to stop
blaming pain
for a problem for the problem
so why is pain a problem you realize no
why do I have a problem with pain
that's a more I could have question
there's pain in itself isn't the problem
but there is a problem in regard to the
pain why is that because the pain is not
wanted why why is the pain not wanted
okay I wanted it well why would you want
it them why do you have to either want
or not want
why can you just be a quantum of see in
regard to either
okay I don't want pain but I don't not
not want pain either
anything big or small far or near past
future any
ad studios any pain
if you stop trying to get rid of it
then the attitude towards pleasure
becomes also apparent
stop trying to entertain it stop trying
to make it so longer stop trying to get
more of it
so automatically by by by discerning the
nature of your attitude towards pain you
also start discerning the nature else
you towards pleasure the gratuitous
assumption of sensuality
sensual desire and pleasure you get from
it that doesn't mean you you stop
perceiving agreeable and disagreeable
things but that's one thing another thing is
but that's one thing another thing is
craving for more of it and craving for
their absence and craving for your
distraction
so if a nature of pain ceases to be a
problem for a person
they've nothing else to do
because it doesn't matter where it comes
from from what sense from what thought
from what experience from what
circumstance pain is not resisted pain
is not feared
pain is not wanted either
because sometimes people would go the
other way and Overland out pain has a
mean of showing that you know know if
pain is a reason it
doesn't matter that's not a problem it's
a secondary thing so if pain arises on
account of your
restraint and determination and
willpower you have no problem with it
he's paying arises on account of
somebody abusing you
offending you whatever you have no
problem with it either
but you don't allow yourself to be
abused well you allow yourself to be
abused when you give in to the attitude
towards pain you become abused that's
the whole point you
like yeah the circumstances are abusive
you are not abused until you put the
projection on the circumstances for that
abuse if you realize that abuse the abuse is
if you realize that abuse the abuse is
founded upon your attitude towards the
experienced feeling at the time so if
their attitude is attitude I don't want
this you made yourself affected by that
abuse so
sexual abuse and sexual well how can you
be sexually abused the body can be
sexual abused physically abuse that's
the kind of normal sexual relationship
exactly yeah which means that people
Gertrudis they take the ownership of the
body to be theirs but we all know how
that ends sickness aging and death which
means it was a mistake to take me as
yours and you better undo that mistake
while you're alive and
you're reflective if this body would
truly mind
in the same sense when I said the
feelings were truly yours you're at it
should be the first and your feelings
will be determined by it
not your attitude will be determined by
the corresponding feeling that has a
reason means oh so my attitude is
secondary to this yet it's acting like
it's some sort of commander-in-chief
so me resisting pain is my attitude
towards there is a pain which has a
reason on its own so if I were to
develop the attitude of hold on that's
not a problem and I stopped culturally
resisting it you won't be able to suffer
in the same sense the body gets somebody
attacks you beat you up physically
that's one thing but you
through gratuitous assumption of the
ownership of their body that's how you
become beaten up and abused
doesn't matter what type of assault and
abuse it is the point is it can be done
only to the body
only today literally to this this bag of
bag of skin filled with lots of other
organs and things and
and
you thinking that you had to say
ultimate say in what befalls dead body
well there was you're ignorant from the
start so even if you never get physically
so even if you never get physically
abused
you will be abused your body will be
abused by aging sickness and death that's the
by aging sickness and death that's the
ultimate abuse no matter of physical
abuse if it doesn't kill you can amount
for the dear views of death
that is inevitable for everyone
but if you realize that the attitude of
abuse comes from you accepting the
ownership of the body that has been
abused and you accept it through wanting
pleasure through it and you accept it
through wanting to get rid of the pain
through it
so it comes down again to the to the
feelings of the present
it's unpleasant feeling of abuse I
mean you don't even think twice before
you start blaming the feeling will
happen to the body and everything else
but if you had enough mindfulness in
self-reflection you realize that yeah
it's unfortunate but that's the subject
of elements
form is being deformed by elements by
other other bodies other things there's
just nature life a sickness aging death
whatever accidents that's the nature of
it
and it was actually my mistake to assume
that I have the same domain
to courteously entertain the attitude of
saying no to this or saying yes someone
more of this
whereby have no saying arising of those
things how can I have the same
prolonging it or not arising in the
first place
how can you have a say in
not wanting a rising of pain
when any attitude towards pain requires
pain first
that's why it's unpleasant that's what
you suffer because of the discrepancy
you know because of the pain
suffering is the discrepancy there your
attitude creates in regard to the
present feeling so the feeling is
pleasurable you suffer when you want more of it and
you suffer when you want more of it and
the discrepancy there is pleasant
feeling and wanting more of it as in not
enough of it
but if you were to stop wanting more of
it then you're gonna have only you're
gonna have a pleasant feeling so there's
no discrepancy no suffering
consequently you have the unpleasant
feeling present soft pain is present and
you don't want that present at all
which means you're overdoing it now
there is some pain but your attitude
does not want any of it and that's
another discrepancy you created it
because there is because there is pain
exactly if all you had is your attitude
towards pain you would be in control but
no there is the actual pain there and
it's your attitude that contradicts it
no this pain must not be while the pain
is oh
this suffer this pleasure must be
greater while it isn't
this neutral feeling what neutral
feeling but there is a neutral feeling
but you're not seeing any interfering
that's another discrepancy
that's why when you aboard you know you
feel unpleasant when there is when
you're bored basically you feel neither
pleasure nor own pleasure but that in
itself it's unpleasant for you you want
to feel something because a threshold
off of your discernment of feeling is
pain and pleasure you don't even see the
neutral one and that's why it's
unpleasant so it's a slightly subtle discrepancy
so it's a slightly subtle discrepancy
but nevertheless it's a discrepancy
probably nervous present yeah then you
stop contradicting it no contradiction
no discrepancy no discrepancy no
suffering suffering is discrepancy created
suffering is discrepancy created
when your attitude clashes with the
world basically a
world can present itself only in three
forms agreeable disagreeable in neutral
and if you deal on that level you don't
have to worry about anything else more
particular than that
you take responsibility for what I was
being felt as in this is felt
by me because of my attitude towards it
I'm making the feeling affect me feeling
of pleasure feeling of pain neutral
feeling if somebody says something
upsetting and to stopping the pain
arises that's not
that's not
that pain is not in what's being said
it's not in that person it's not in any
of the circumstances it's in your
attitude in regard to the circumstances
so you have to take responsibility for
suffering basically you don't have to
take responsibility for agreeable and
disagreeable but you have to take
responsibility for wanting agreeable and
not wanting disagreeable what I mean by
taking responsibility means seeing that
it's on you there's no excuse is mine
yes it's my doing I'm responsible for
this so when I suffer I'm responsible
for that only through that attitude you
can actually get a glimpse at least and
maybe even you know go through with it
you can figure out how to not suffer but
for as long as your attitude doesn't
take on suffering as
your responsibility
and conflates suffering with
disagreeable circumstances with painful
circumstances you're not gonna see the
nature of suffering how can you free
yourself from it
so you have to stop blaming painful
circumstances for your suffering suffering is not a
for your suffering suffering is not a
pain
so there is pain without suffering but
they cannot be suffering without the
pain
so if you remove your attitude of denial
and trying to get rid of the pain you
won't suffer
if you remove your attitude and
indulgent in regard to the pleasure you
won't suffer
you won't suffer on account of either
pfizer pleasure or pain or neutral feel
the more you do that well the more you
like this attitude is maintained through
through not knowing it super seriously
assuming it at face value and
exactly well that's all you can do you
can't decide to stop okay now I will
stop trying to get rid of the feeling of
fun pleasure that's impossible
but understanding your attitude towards
it that attitude is being gradually
canceled out of your pain I feel pain
mind jumps to blame the circumstances
you recognize that wait a minute how
many times does it happen how many times
really happen do I ever say in
circumstances no why do I then keep sort
of
like inflaming myself with this attitude
yeah this or this or that present we
just you just feeds the fire further
while I kind of know already that that's
not the problem that's all they like
indignation and anger and the codings
constant maintenance needs constant
action to make it valid constant blame
constant blame
find them find the scapegoat for this
T's fault is that false who's gonna pay
for this
yeah there are mistakes and people do
things that are on and they're
responsible for that but if you suffer
on account of it that responsibility
solely yours said buddy
the sickness show me you have to
yeah that's so fun you can be managing
the circumstances but you don't want to
be doing it out of a out of trying to
get rid of the suffering because that
inquires you identifying suffering with
disagreeable circumstances of an ailing
body and
how do you know whether you're acting
out of it or not well ask yourself what
if I don't take the medicine what if I
don't go and see the doctor am I gonna
get filled with anxiety and fear in
regards to this and we're gonna suffer
and we're gonna experience mental
anguish basically if the answer is yes
means you are still conflating suffering
with circumstances
no no well then you realize whether you
give up the medicines or not that's not
a problem
the problem is you confusing you're
suffering with disagreeable feeling that
has a reason on the level of an ailing
body but you are making it into your mental
but you are making it into your mental
anguish
because of the gratuitous attitude of
trying to get rid of it
so then you can take a step further and
reflect okay so this is the work that
needs to be done in order to do their
work I need to stay alive saute the
medicine that's like properly
that's like properly
reflecting then you take the medicine
there's like a borrowing the time so
that you cannot have to do the problem
but you don't take the medicine out of
that blind blind sort of just jump into
it I'm sick fear deal with it okay and
then I'll practice you gotta look after
your tools
the body's a tool on account of which
you can understand the nature of the
body the nature of non ownership and so
on and for that you need it
keep it in a certain so that's why we
say he wisely avoids a wild elephant
the one who practices down he was the
avoids a snake a child called pit while
a pack of dogs because it would be
foolish before he has completed the work
to ignore the fact that this might kill
him
but you don't you know you don't go
around with an attitude of health is
good in itself as in the health is the
greatest ready well you're gonna be
sorely disappointed
so health is basically a tool
and then you realize okay
my house is not perfect but the tune is
still good enough
and you can also then realize that
you're able to go quite far with the
attitude that it's good enough because
it is good enough and it comes down to
well as long as I'm still alive and you
know my senses are still there it's
still good enough even if you're in pain
and discomfort
why would you do that
like if somebody hasn't has they thought
where would that action intention be
rooted right there and then
right there and then
so you realize I don't need to go out
because I just now revealed to myself
that I'm trying to get rid of the
suffering by thinking I'll go out and do
this and this and
that's what you get rid of suffering
will you recognize your attitude in
regard to the disagreeable feeling which
is always well there's a feeling oh
yes the work is always the work is
always present in the sense of
being mindful of the attitude toward the
present feeling
anyway to be mindful the present feeling
you have to stop blaming the
circumstances for the arising of that
feeling you have to take responsibility
for it you have to feel it basically you
have to allow it to be felt not try to
get rid of it
well you can't be mindful of the craving
as I'm clear and clinically you can be
mindful the feeling and then this learn
the nature of it
well can I as I said my attitude is
always second to this there is no it's
inconceivable to be different
once that which you have been
prioritized which will be prioritizing
it's in a second
it's not a priority anymore
and if their attitude another priority
that's how the attitude starts to fade
so to being mindful of the enduring
feeling you get to discern the nature of
the feeling that's what mindfulness is
the basis of knowledge
or like pain or restraint say no to
yourself say no to sensual indulgence saying no
say no to sensual indulgence saying no
to laziness say no to your will acting
out of ill-will it produces pain
because there is that discrepancy oh I
want to do this but you say no but again
where is the discrepancy really rooted
is rooted in you want this and saying no
to it or is it rooted it you want this
saying no to this let's experience
disagreeable disagreeably that you don't
want
so circumstances arising say
like a prospect of ill will but you
restrain yourself as a result of that
you're experiencing this pain now
unpleasant feeling that's what you're
resisting so circumstances were not a
problem even wanting to act out of it wasn't a
even wanting to act out of it wasn't a
problem
it became a problem when circumstances
they were unpleasant
you wanted to get rid of the this
pleasure through affecting the
circumstances that's what you're gonna
shout beat people up threaten them so they
beat people up threaten them so they
never ever say that to you again
but if you were not affected by the
feeling of what's being said how could
you even conceive after we will and
same as we spoke in many other talks
sensuality as well the first
the first relationship with central
prospect every mind that Universal is
pain that's essential it is so intoxicating
that's essential it is so intoxicating
because it's felt very unpleasantly and
if you give into it not just that you
avoid that well did you cover up that
pain but you get more pleasure out of it
so it feels like a double pleasure
but you realize that sensuality is
maintained and people go with say you
know I'll follow the tastes or sexuality
or just just careless in thousands of
the senses because it's very painful
when the prospect of of sensual
indulgence present itself it's felt very
painfully to not give in
and automatically you blame your
attitude of not giving in for the pain
but you realize wait a minute my
attitude is a negative attitude like I'm
not doing anything
negative attitude means sensuality has a
reason hey go and eat all these cakes
that you want now that's a thought so
you're not actually eating the case
which means you're still not doing
anything so your response is a negative
response not a bad response in a negative like oh
not a bad response in a negative like oh
it's bad no it means it's basically not
a positive action it's a it's a call to
a positive action go and go and get
these cakes and eat them and enjoy the
sense of taste you get from it now all
of that is still at your thought and you
are not eating it you're not making any
effort so it's a negative experience its
so it's a negative experience its
absence of these cakes they will provide
me with these great pleasures and
that's the pain of it
it's because of your attitude that
always welcomes greater pleasure from
the currently experienced feeling
so then the prospect of greater pleasure
immediately the experiences that great
discrepancy and
when people would give in go and get all
these cakes and overeat and what not
because they want to avoid the pain
in the first place
but can you really
avoid as in can you really prevent the
pain in the first place by doing that
what can you just covering it up and
distract yourself from it
and you realize you can't avoid it you
realize that by giving in value to the
joy that comes out of taste treating all
these cakes in this example you gave in
the value you confirmed that you were
affected by it in the first place by
that pain of not having that sensuality
so as we said before people think
sensuality is unpleasant because they
say no to it
but it's other way around
you say no to sensuality you realize
that the pain that you've been
attributing to you saying no as in not
giving into the positive action
the pain of it is basically in that
positive action so if you want to get
rid of sensuality and pain of sensuality
and dependence and pressure and burden
and all of it you just need to stick to
saying no to it and then the nature of
it will become apparent
because you're not doing I said you're
not doing anything now and the thought
of sensuality comes the restraint is
closer to the natural state you were
before you are not doing anything
but it's the thought of sensuality that
pressures you to go and do it and
the pain arises on account of that
that's the discrepancy that's being
created
because you were not doing anything
before sexuality and you're not doing
anything when you're restraining
sensuality so that's the constant there what has
so that's the constant there what has
changed is absence of sensuality
before the pain and then presence of
sensuality when the pain is there Sunil
is wait a minute it's the presence or
absence of sensuality
craving for that pleasure
that's what creates the discrepancy of
pain of suffering on account sensuality
not my restraint my restraint is more
like emulation of the proper behavior of
the proper action of the action that
doesn't give in to the to the pressure
of sensuality or awareness on that's why
the restraint self composure virtue has
to come first because it starts
emulating things rightly you don't know
yet but on that ground you can get to
know it
so inevitably pain is going to be felt
when you send out to sensuality and you
have to accept it
once you accept it then you can say
basically to the pain and to yourself
the death pain belongs to the sensuality
not to the restraint of it
because the said restraint is that- it's
no action there it's abstaining from
action so you you've been abstaining from
so you you've been abstaining from
central action when there were no
sensuality pressuring you now since
Charlotte is pressuring you you're
practicing restraint okay you're on the
same level of abstaining from direction
yet there is pain what's different it's
absence or presence of sensuality and
then it becomes even more apparent the
one thing for sure you'll never find
peace and like ultimate freedom in a
sense of not being pressured by
circumstances if you keep engaging with sensuality
if you keep engaging with sensuality
we could reduce cravings of pleasure
through senses
we gratuitous expressions of your
ill-will three or sensitive
so whether sensuality touches you
whether you will touches you where the
boredom touches you what they all have
in common pain
it's a disagreeable experience
having an attitude of wanting to get rid
of disagreeable
means what
in sensuality how do you get rid of
disagreeable by saying yes to it
he knew well how do you get rid of the
disagreeable by affecting the person or whatever
by affecting the person or whatever
circumstances by saying yes to it
exactly in boredom how'd you get rid of
disagreeable by saying yes to it and
finding things to distract yourself from
it either way you have a positive
attitude result in positive actions of
indulgence ill-will distraction greed
aversion delusion not metaphysical
things the things that your attitudes
are based on your actions based on
because of your attitude in regard to
how you're feeling so
from that point of view that's what
Buddha meant whatever it's felt counts
at suffering
because feeling of agreeable pressures you
feeling of agreeable pressures you
feeling of disagreeable pressures you
feel the mutual pleasures you
but again that pressure is not in the
feeling or on the feeling that pressure
is in your ignorance of it
so you are pressured in regard to
pleasure because you haven't understood
it you are pressured in regard to the
displeasure cause you haven't understood
it
same goes for the neutral feeling and
that's exactly what I said if the
neutral feeling is not understood its
felt unpleasantly pressures there if the
neutral feeling is understood there is
no pressure it's felt pleasantly
so you want sensuality in order to be
free from pain you have ill-will and
anger in order to be free from pain
you have distraction boredom indolence
laziness in order to be free from pain
wanting to be free from pain
if you stop equating that with trying to
get rid of this pain
then you can actually learn how to free
yourself from pain from being affected
by pain
so you will truly be free from pain not
when pain stops arising but when your
attitude towards pain changes
so that's that's again just to also add
to what you said you have to go out
seeking out suffering and pain just say
no to your desires and the pains there
you don't need to gonna risk your life
until threatened and get you know that a
substantial dread going just that say no
to your daily sense desires and you'll
see how quickly the pain will come
knocking on your door
that's I mean if the air attitude is
developed towards pain is not the
problem it's my attitude towards pain
that's problem
then no amount of pain can prevail over
the mind that's what it will mean for
another hunt the disagreeable feelings
cannot overwhelm his mind he is the one
who overwhelms his mind overwhelms the
disagreeable feelings well he's in one
horror once his mind in regards to
disagreeable feelings and that's not
just that he needs to do that is like
it's some sort of you know determination
sort of willpower practice no
understanding that's just the natural
state of affairs but disagreeable arises
he has a reason overwhelmed by the mind
that has understood it
basically understanding overwhelms the
understanding overwhelms the
disagreeable presence of understanding
automatically is higher than this
agreeable or agreeable or neutral so no
none of those feelings can overwhelm it
anymore cause it's not on the level of
just I'm doing this it's on the level of
this this thing this paint is there
there is the understanding of that pain
is there simultaneously with that pain
understand me you understand what's
there so that understanding depends on
was there but whenever that thing is
there he has been understood right there
and then because it's there
no because you theorized about it and
rationally the body no it's because it's
there that would be an understood
presence of that thing presence of of
agreeable feeling presence of
disagreeable feeling and this just
another way of saying there is no more
attitude there is no more assumed almost entitled
there is no more assumed almost entitled
attitude in regard to pleasure pain or
neutral so then pleasure feels pleasantly
so then pleasure feels pleasantly
displeasure feels unpleasantly a
neutral feeling it feels neutral and
there is no suffering in regard to any
so we started by saying why is paying
the problem but why am I making a
problem out of pain same what am i
making problem out of out of pleasure
like well all know make about where you
are because you are pressured by it
if pleasure is truly not a problem
you wouldn't suffer on account of not
getting enough of it
whichever shape or form pleasure would
arise you will be self sufficient to that
you will be self sufficient to that
extent
there would be no craving for more
sensual pleasure
so you have a thought of as we said of
going and eating up all the nice sweet
cakes that thought is agreeable it's nice nice
that thought is agreeable it's nice nice
cakes nice nice taste
but that's it in itself that's
sufficient why would not that thought
pressure you to go make all these
actions finally cake and cake eating cake
finally cake and cake eating cake
consuming it all of that
means you were affected by that pleasure
on the level of your thought
because you were affected the only means
of you dealing with being pressured and
and and and experiencing disagreeable
he's seeking out what it but it sort of
points at the cake at the mouth and
eating shoving cake in your mouth all
that but all that secondary to the thought of
but all that secondary to the thought of
that
pleasure of the taste
but if you were indifferent to the
pleasure of the taste on the level of
the thought
committing actions on account of it
becomes inconceivable there doesn't mean
that you don't recognize this is a tasty
cake and this is not a tasty food
but none of that experience can then
almost like facilitate further
actions for its own sake that's why
central craving and central pleasure
always remains bound with the level of
the thought
because the only reason you'll be going
there and doing this and eating like it
because the context of the thought of
consuming a tasty food is still there
giving the meaning to all of your
individual actions of getting there
that's why once you go and eat the cake
you never can fulfill that thought
because thought is a thought and taste
is a taste two completely different
sense but you were assuming this
identity of the whole projection the
whole action
thought of a pleasant taste consumption
of the pleasant taste it's identified
but deep down it isn't and you know that
and that's obvious to everyone everybody
will say people who never read goodies
or anything yeah you know at the time
really satisfy your desires can't you
because there's nothing to satisfy
there is a pleasure initial pleasure on
the level of the thought that's it but
it's your attitude that
automatically wants more pleasure so you
think more about it
there wants more pleasure so you go and
do something about it so
again it's attitude of wanting more
pleasure in regard to the thought of
pleasure that's the discrepancy that's being
that's the discrepancy that's being
created at there so that attitude is why
you suffer that attitude is why you
assume the whole world of sensuality
but if you undo the attitude of
automatically wanting welding pleasure
and automatically not wanting pain then
you have an agreeable thought of
or some nice very like tasty food or
agreeable thought of some beautiful
music or agreeable thought of beautiful
sights that's it they're just beautiful
things that you thought about
and then agree ability of them stays
with them there is no attitude of you I
want more of this and that's why in the
stall in the in the in the thought they
will be only the thought in the sight
they will be only this side in the sound
do you hear something pleasant that
pleasure is confined to that pleasure
because you don't interfere with it
through your attitude of wanting more of
it you
don't need to favorite it through
attitude of trying to get rid of it so
in the scene they've just been the scene
in the herd they're just be the herd the
buck you stood the famous by hairsuit
now because you got so absorbed in the
scene that there's only the scene no
it's because in the scene they can only
be the scene you can't have the
something else in the scene know if it's
there it's seen
you can't have the heard in the scene of
the told in the scene
in as much you can't have the scene in
the thought
and that's not saying that's why
sensualities on the level of the mind
and that's with a set but even for the
that's with a set but even for the
target ah the beautiful things remain in
the world but it's the desire and lost
his thought and desire and lust has been
perpetuated through it that's what he
has a rooted
so thought of sensual pleasure is
agreeable on the level of the thought
and
you recognize that is that is the extent
of his gratification that that initial
agree ability that's as much as you can
get from it
so if you remove the attitude towards
wanting more of it you remove any basis
for spreading of sensuality
if there is no spreading of sensuality
sensuality will cease because it
requires maintenance a
video requires maintenance ignorance
requires maintenance
here will if there is a thought of I've
been offended he said something rude to
me or all these people might come and
kill me
if you're not trying to get rid of the
displeasure of that thought
you won't be affected by anything that
happens through that port and you
certainly won't be able to engage with
anything and also
that's why I wouldn't be able to kill
somebody even in self-defense you just
wouldn't it's nothing to defend
so why is pain not wanted why's pleasure
wanted
it's not about getting rid of the
pleasure or having more of it it's about
getting rid of the pain making it never
appear it's about not wanting one and
not trying to get rid of the other
that's it
now you can't say you have a say you
have a thought as we said or eating some
some tasty food and then you're full-on
chugging food down down down your throat
just swallowing it and saying to
yourself let's see I don't want it on
the level of my thought that's that's
inconceivable that's a contradiction in
terms that's what I'm gonna said it's
impossible to engage physically with
sensuality without having sensual
perceptions on the level of top thought
you just come
hence the sense restrain the physical
restraint needs to come first
because it's based on the wrong
discrepancy so engaging with it you're
affirming the discrepancy if you are
affirming the discrepancy you're
affirming suffering how can you get rid
of suffering when you're affirming it
through your own bare reactions
you're building up on something you take
something as your temptation yeah
exactly which means any of your efforts cannot
which means any of your efforts cannot
really pertain to suffering to undoing
of it
trying to get rid of it
trying to get rid of this perpetuation
of the attitude that creates the problem
that's what meant your attitude creates
the problem and problem perpetuates it
once created and but there is no first
point what the problem was in Crick was
creating wasn't before there's no first
point to a region oh
you can just think about pain as we
started because if you remove the
attitude of not wanting pain you're
automatically dealing with sensuality
with pleasure and with pain and we deal
well
because you would give in to sensuality
because it's unpleasant to not do so
so the way of getting rid of that
displeasure is by doing so
but what if you're not affected by that
displeasure in the first place
can you realize oh it's not for me to
use you know there's nothing for me to
be engaged with
and technologies pleasant once you're
given into it
but you want to look as to why did you
have to give into it because it was
painful and everybody knows that
so that's with like we spoke before with
the willpower and so on that's why you
should use willpower
public saying no to everything and
overcoming and making him luck you know
prevailing over every single no
just find things on account of which you
suffer which is your attitude in regard
to pleasure your attitude in regard to
pain your attitude in regard to neither
pleasure nor pain
and ya prevail there that's it
you have to worry about anything else
then because whatever you do won't be
unwholesome because it's only routine in
trying to get rid of the pain
it's not rooted in the discrepancy
hence it's our own ignorance and our own
actions rooted in it they're
perpetuating it that is obscuring the
nature of things as they actually are
so you remove your
discrepant attitude or attitude that
results in discrepancy they created that
generates it then you see the way things
are in the scene this is just the same
whenever anything there never was
anything more they couldn't have been
anything more in the in the felt there
was just a felt in the perceived there
was the perceived in the intended there
was intended nothing else
in the world there was just a world
so in that sense you can truly learn
from your pain
whatever that pain is
not through like psychologizing and
developing some nice pleasing theories
as you're learning inverted commas know
with presence of pain you automatically
simultaneously must have presence of
director tutors attitude unless you are
fully enlightened
so the presence of disagreeable you have
a basis for I'm doing your attitude
towards the disagreeable
and yeah pain is a great teacher if done
right if you know how to look at it if
you have a right view
because if you know where to look then
all you have to do is
practice composure
self-control restraint because all these
things will be revealing
the nature of feelings that are
experienced unpleasantly we'll be
revealing the displeasure of sensuality
the displeasure well well we'll be
revealing it not creating it
and once you reveal the the displeasure
that was making you have the attitude
towards getting rid of the displeasure
you start don't do the attitude
automatically
it is always because it's always
something felt which means there's
always attitude in regard to whatever is
being felt
if you fix things on the most
fundamental level everything else built
up will be fixed equally if you purify
the stream and it's very origin top of
the mountain
eventually even the rivers and seas
they're being filled by that stream will
be purified but you can be battling and
trying to purify the rivers down there
down the mountain while there is still
the source of pollution remains
and that's how you know in the wheel
said he purifies his mind from
unwholesome thoughts from thoughts of
sensuality that's exactly it's done not
by chasing every individual I was
thinking this what I didn't mean they
would know what is the nature of this
was rooted in trying to get rid of the
pain caused by sensual pleasure prospect
essential pleasure was it rooted in
trying to get rid of the pain caused by
something disagreeable
what they're trying to get rid of the
pain caused by something agreeable was
they're trying to get rid of the pain
caused by neutral either way it's gonna
be either sensuality it will or delusion
so
he doesn't entertain it on that level
and that's how he purifies his behavior
in every other regard